<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secret policy of the Iansenists, and the present state of the Sorbon. Discovered by a doctour of that faculty, who having learnt Iansenisme when he studied divinity, vnder a master that taught it there publickly, has been since disabused, &amp; followes the Catholick party. / Translated out of the French copie.</title>
            <title>Secrette politiqve des Iansenistes et l'estat present de la Sorbonne de Paris. English</title>
            <author>Deschamps, Etienne Agard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82031</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578317</idno>
  <idno type="VID">172251</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240868237</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D516A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">45578317</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2621:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secret policy of the Iansenists, and the present state of the Sorbon. Discovered by a doctour of that faculty, who having learnt Iansenisme when he studied divinity, vnder a master that taught it there publickly, has been since disabused, &amp; followes the Catholick party. / Translated out of the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Secrette politiqve des Iansenistes et l'estat present de la Sorbonne de Paris. English</title>
                  <author>Deschamps, Etienne Agard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Christian Roman, at the Sign of True Faith near the great Church.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Troyes, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. LXVII. [i.e. 1667]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Deschamps by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Université de Paris.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Jansenists.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172251:1"/>
            <p>THE SECRET POLICY OF THE IANSENISTS, AND THE PRESENT STATE OF THE SORBON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DISCOVERED BY A DOCTOVR of that Faculty,</hi> Who having learnt Iansenisme when he studied Divinity, vnder a Master that taught it there publickly, has been since disabused, &amp; followes the Catholick party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated out of the French Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at TROYES, By CHRISTIAN ROMAN, at the Sign of true Faith near the great Church.</p>
            <p>M.DC.LXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172251:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Chevallier des <hi>TROIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PONTS</hi> having given me the perusal of this writing, which was composed by a friend of his, a Doctour of Paris, after his conversion, to satisfy some questions which be had proposed vnto him: I thought good, with his leave, to print it that Catholicks may with more ease, avoid the snares of the Iansenists, when they see them layd open, &amp; thos Doctors of Sorbon, who have suffered themselves to be surprized, may follow their brothers example, in their conversion, &amp; purge their Faculty of Iansenisme.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:172251:2"/>
            <head>THE SECRET POLICY OF THE ANSENISTS, TO THE CHEVALIER DES TROISPONTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE progresse which Jansenisme makes in France, would infinitly astonish me, did I not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that Calvinisme planted it self ther, with as great facility &amp; <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uccesse, as d'Avila observes wel in his histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the civill wars. <hi>Book.</hi> 1. <hi>edit.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 36.37. He says that Calvins opinions were receaved with passion, &amp; maintaind with obstinacy, by <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great many persons of all conditions: That <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he city of Geneva was the prime seat of his <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>octrine: That Books were printed ther, &amp; <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ispersed into the Provinces by witty &amp; elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uent persons, who made it their busines to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roach his heresy: That by degrees, it spread <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t self over all the Towns &amp; Provinces of the
<pb facs="tcp:172251:3"/>kingdome, though this was don so secretly, that litle apeard in publick besides weak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures. <hi>pag.</hi> 38. That in all the Parliaments, ther were many counsellours infected with thes opinions: That already a world of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of both sexes had been seduced by the sermons of Theodore Beza a Disciple of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin &amp; one of the most knowing &amp; eloquent men of his time: That many great Persons had also suffered themselves to be drawn into the same belief. <hi>Book</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 57. That ther were many even amongst the Prelats, whos inclinations carried them to hearken after Calvins opinions. <hi>Book</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 36. The reason he alleages for it, is the natural curiosity which French men have to please themselves with novelties. I could attribute the propagation of this heresy, to the same cause; if we were not in so learned an age, which has light e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to disperse all errours, with as much facility, as the sun-beames drive away dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
            <p>Sure the wonderful Policy, of the Authors &amp; followers of this Sect, may justly challenge all the glory of its encrease And because Sir, you desire me to discover vnto you the who<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>secret,</hi> I will do it by thos lights which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved, when they had no cause to conceal them from me &amp; by the effects which are
<pb facs="tcp:172251:3"/>known to the whole world; the reasons I say which moved them &amp; the method which they have followed to accomplish their design. But to proceed orderly, I will first shew the end they proposed to themselves &amp; then treat of the means they have vsed to compass it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The end which the Iansenists proposed to themselves.</head>
               <p>Some Authors think they had a good mind to abolish the belief of the Incarnation of the Eternal word, and of all other truths re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to it, that is to say all Christianity. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers maintain that they are willing enough, to keep an outward apearance of Christian Religion, but that they mean in reality to destroy it by overthrowing her doctrine &amp; Sacraments. Others are of opinion that they intend to establish the faith of one God, but lay aside all other articles which we recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve. They all seem to bring probable reasons to prove their assertions. One amongst the rest and one of the most knowing has ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of their writings, Sermons, and practise in administring the Sacraments, thes following propositions, over and a bove thos five which are condemned.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That since the year 400 after CHRIST, ther has been no true Church.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172251:4"/> 2. That Indulgences are to be layd aside as human inventions as also the worship of the Virgen Mother of God, of Saints and Images: private Masses, Confession of venial sins, &amp; the vse of the Holy Eucharist.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That invincible ignorance, &amp; not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, does not excuse from sinn.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That all the actions of one in mortal sinn, for example his prayers, almesdeeds, the honour he gives to his parents &amp;c. are mortal sins.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the vse of Marriage in sterill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whether by age or otherwise, is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally sinfull.</p>
               <p n="6">6 That Bishops cease to be Bishops, &amp; Magistrats to be Magistrats, when they are in mortal sinn.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That we ought to follow what our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour motions suggest against the laws of God &amp; his Church, and of Soveraigns Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That Priests and Curates are equal to Bishops, &amp; Bishops to Popes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That a pennance proportionable to the sinns, is to be performed, before ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution is given. And that even thos that have been absolved in their sicknes before they have made such an equal satisfaction, are bound to make another Confession.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172251:4"/> 10. That vpon this ground they refuse absolution, to thos that are not in the next occasion of sinning, &amp; such as profess a firme &amp; sincere purpose of amendment, obliging them first to perform such pennances.</p>
               <p n="11">11. From hence also they enjoyn most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant, &amp; wild pennances, as to labourers in a vineyard, never to drink wine, to women to lye often, &amp; for many houres, with their bare bellies vpon the ground, which has made some run mad, &amp; shortned the lives of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: To thos that have wronged their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, to ask their pardon for their secret lewdnes: To yong women to put on shifts dipt in water, to pray an hour in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; so go to bed.</p>
               <p>Though thes things are known to many, yet I will write nothing, but what their books &amp; common practise, publish vnto the whol world, least I passe for a suspected person.</p>
               <p>I say then that they have a mind to bring in Calvinisme, into the Catholick Church, which at first sight, does not seem so contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Iesus Christ as some other designs, though it effectually destroy him, leaving nothing to his followers, but the bare name of Christians. This I gather from their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Iansenius his Letters to the Abbot of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172251:5"/>S. Cyran, printed by the Sieur de Preville, reveal this mystery, &amp; convince that his head was full of nothing but Calvinisme, &amp; that they both bent their endeavours, to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thos that will take the pains, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his book entitled <hi>Iansenii Augustinus,</hi> with Calvins Institutions, will soon discover that he has followed his doctrine, his proofs, his discourses, his consequences &amp;c. In so much that he agrees with himself so long as he sticks close to this Arch-heretick, but when he leaves him, he swerves from his own principles in many points.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Iuridical Informations taken against the Abbot of S. Cyran; his Catechisme of Grace; his book of vowes, &amp; other workes of his, which he published vnder borrowed names, prove clearly that he made more voyages to Geneva then to Rome, &amp; that he preferred the errours of the one, before the faith of the other.</p>
               <p>Now since the Iansenists, have stuffed their Letters &amp; their books, with Calvins do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, may we not conclude, that they ayme to introduce Calvinisme, into the church of Christ? And certainly, the five Propositions condemned by the Bishops of Rome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing but rank Calvinisme, entierly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172251:5"/>shut vp in thos five Priniciples, as the root, blade eares, &amp; corne is shut vp in the grain of wheat, which is sowd. Besides in their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Letter, which is printed in Monsieur Marandés Book, <hi>of the Inconveniences proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Iansenisme to the State,</hi> with the means &amp; instructions which they prescribe their followers for the happy settlement of their principles, they say, <hi>that the Chief end of their vnion, is to remove the abuses &amp; disorders, which have crept into the Church, since S. Augustins time, through ignorance of his excellent doctrine.</hi> Where by this holy Fathers doctrin, they vnderstand that of Jansenius, who made vse of his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as Calvin did, to persuade the world, that he varied not from the sentiments of that holy Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE MEANES To arrive at this end.</head>
               <div n="1" type="means">
                  <head>THE FIRST MEANES. <hi>Not to meddle with Calvins odious Propositions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>CAlvinisme being grown very odious to Catholicks, the Jansenists with great prudence thought it necessary, to cut off such things, as have hetherto scandalized the world. And therfore they have rejected thes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172251:6"/>propositions. That God is the Author of sinn; That Christs body is only figuratively in the Eucharist; That ther are but two Sacraments; That the Pope is Anti-Christ. That it is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry to worship Images: That we ought not to pray to the Mother of God, or to the Angels or Saints in Heaven: That ther is no Purgatory; That the Masse is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp;c. On the contrary side, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Priests, a single life, the Masse, seven Sacraments, Church ornaments &amp; ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Pope, the Hierarchy, &amp; in a word all that is popular, because the people, are most taken with that, which strikes the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, &amp; that way stirs vp devotion. And besi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, because they are vsed to be governed by the Pope &amp; by Bishops &amp;c. and accustomed to the Sacraments, to Masse &amp;c. Finally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause experience has taught the Calvinists, that the laying aside such things, has been a great hinderance to the propagation of their Sect. The Jansenists having thus refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Calvinisme, have instilld it without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour &amp; even without distrust, into simple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who easily receave such impressions, as are given them by their teachers, without discovering their subtle disguises.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="means">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172251:6"/>
                  <head>The second Meanes. <hi>To remain in the Communion of the Church.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Yet for all this, they feard, that time, which discovers the most hidden things, would at last make known all their cunning tricks, &amp; so stifle their whol project in its birth; That Catholicks having found out the track of Calvinisme would fly from it with horrour. And that as the Abbot of S. Cyran, sayd <hi>Calvin had a good cause, but knew not how to defend it,</hi> because he had not the knack of declining the name of Heretick, as he might have done, had he not openly forsaken the Churches Communion. For this reason, they layd it for a fundamental Maxime of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, <hi>never to depart out of the Catholicke Church,</hi> &amp; consequently to acknowlege the Pope, and seemingly to submit to the Hierarchical go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. This important resolution, was also grounded, vpon thos reasons, which they took to be convincing. 1. That Pelagius, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius, Eutyches, the Donatists, &amp; all the most prudent Founders of new Sects, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly conserve the name and outward shew of Catholicks, &amp; by that meanes, got the advantages they wished for, whence they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that they ought to follow their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172251:7"/>&amp; would have the like success. 2. That by this meanes, they might without difficulty insinuate themselves, into the esteem of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, of all sexes &amp; conditions in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; secular communities, Universities, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademies, Soveraigne &amp; inferiour Courts of Judicature; Courts of Kings &amp;c. They might also speak converse; preach, write, direct consciences &amp;c. And in this manner infuse their doctrine, establish their Maximes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themselves against their Adversaries vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine their endeavours &amp;c. blow vp all plots against their Sect, oppose them eyther secretly, or with open violence; sow divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; practise a world of other artifices, to disunite &amp; confound their enemies. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is, because while they remain exteriour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnited to the Church, they will not be suspected, but will easily passe for friends, &amp; yet may act the part of enemies, as being cloaked with the apearance of a true &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere friendship. 3. That men born &amp; bred, in civil or Ecclesiastical Societies, do not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily leave them, to follow strange companies. And so we see many Hereticks, when they are convinced of their errours, to alleage this, for the only obstacle to their conversion: That it is hard for men to renounce their Religion, to embrace that which they take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172251:7"/>to be false, &amp; destructive of that faith, which they have allways professed But if they may be permitted, to conserve the forme &amp; exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour of their first Society, they are engaged by litle &amp; litle, in the changes, which are brought in. The same we see in States, that Subjects suffer the change of their lawes &amp; Customes, &amp; of the whol government, when it is done by degrees, &amp; so, as so retain in many things the apearance of the same States. Why then might not they, by remaining in the Catholick Church, by litle &amp; litle chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the ancient doctrine, &amp; bring in their new inventions in place therof. 4. That in case they should be condemned by the Pope, they might wipe off the blemish, by seeming to leave their party, &amp; yet secretly adhere to it, &amp; withal conserve their friendship, whom they had gained to their cabal, before their condemnation. 5. That contrariwise, if they should separate themselves from the Church, their name would be infamous, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation suspected, their Books discredited, their defence slighted, their whol doctrin odious, &amp; consequently, it would not be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for them, to set vp their new Sect. Thes. judicious reasons, have not deceaved their hopes, for infinite Catholicks have been il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, &amp; drawn to their opinions, while they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172251:8"/>lay covered vnder the sacred vayle of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="means">
                  <head>The third Meanes. <hi>An inviolable secrecy &amp; dissimulation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>But because Catholicks of this age, are too clear sighted, to be cozend with the poyson of Calvinisme, when it shall be offerd them they agreed amongst themselves, according to S. Cyrans Maxime, who (was wont to cry, <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum meum mihi propter metum Iudaeorum, id est, Catholicorum;</hi>) to hide it so cunningly, that the craftiest of vs all should not find it out. To this purpose they proposed divers ways, to give it the ayre and colour of Catholicisme, amongst others, thes were judged to be the best. 1. To give out that it is Saint Austins doctrine. 2. Not to communicate it to such as are suspected, or neutrals, or adversaries, but in ambiguous tearms. 3. To advance obscure propositions of Predestination, of Grace, of Liberty &amp;c. without explicating them, to draw on the curiosity of such as are lovers of novelties. 4. To persuade the world that they pretend only to reforme the loos doctrin and corrupt manners of the Church. 5. To call their adversaries <hi>Pelagians</hi> &amp; <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelagians;</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172251:8"/>that their disputes may passe only for Scholastical questions. It was for this that Jansenius with so much cunning writt the History of thes Hereticks in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his <hi>Augustinus,</hi> and that they stiled their enemies <hi>Molinists.</hi> Now the reasons of this proceeding are thes. That few are will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to engage in particular quarreis: That all, on the contrary, greedily read the works of opposite parties, to passe their judgment on them. That not being able to remain neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals, they easily side with one of the parties. That they commonly stand for novelty, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when it is smoothd over with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary devotion &amp; good language. That the will being once gaind, it is easy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay the fals lights of their new doctrine into their vnderstanding, because in disputes about Religion, the will commonly governs the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, as she commands it to submit vnto the obscure truthes of faith. 6. But to catch Catholiks with more ease, in thes pretended particular disputes; they further agreed, to make them passe for the debates between the <hi>Thomists</hi> &amp; the <hi>Iesuits.</hi> Did not their Depuries, who argued their cause at Rome, before Innocent X. actually make the Masters of the sacred Palace, &amp; learned Wad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding believe it, and were they not afterwards
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172251:9"/>disabused and checked by his Holines, for vnwarily falling into the Jansenists nets? 7. Though thes meanes are efficacious, yet following the maxime of certain Italians, <hi>divide if you mean to raign</hi> &amp; the practise of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, who raysed warr in Catholicke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the better to settle themselves in the common troubles: they thought it necessary to rayse a spiritual warr amongst Catholicks, to divide them, &amp; set them one against an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that so they might intrigue themselves in the designs, of that partie which could best help them against their enemies. This made the Abbot of S. Cyran write his Book of the Hierarchy vnder the name of <hi>Petrus Aurelius,</hi> to set Priests &amp; Prelats against Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. It was for this that they set vp the questions of Masse in the Parish Church, Confessions at Easter, and of thos that are sick, of the Regulars Privileges, of the right to direct consciences &amp;c. to force some to fall vpon others, and them to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in lieu of joyning their forces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to destroy their new doctrine. They did not question but to reap fruit out of thes civil warrs, &amp; to settle their particular opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the heate of thes common disputes. 8. Verily it was no easy matter, to discover so subtle a design: yet they judged this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172251:9"/>so necessary that to render it quite im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penetrable, they resolved 1. To affect a state<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and mysterious eloquence, full of proofs stuft with plausible expressions, but of a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; obscure sense. 2. To give two biasses to their designs and opinions, that as occasion should serve they might follow that which was most commodious. 3. Not to trust this secret with above two or three in a Town, &amp; thos of the most capable of their Proselites. 4. To make their assemblies walking abroad to take the aire, when they are to consult a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their affaires. 5. Not to set their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to their printed Books, that they may disown them, when it makes for the interest of their Partie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="means">
                  <head>The fourth Meanes. <hi>To be neat &amp; in good esteem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Things being thus contrived, they fel to spruce vp themselves, to become fitter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute their designs. It was a clear case with them, that being to convers with the world, they were to go always very compleat in their apparel, &amp; be careful that nothing but neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes apeard in their words &amp; outward garbe: They were to reform their manners, at least
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172251:10"/>in the exteriour, &amp; practise certain mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, to please thos they hoped to gain to their partie, &amp; to give a tast of the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their doctrine. They were to draw the people to certain exteriour practises of piety, as to help &amp; visite the sick and priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to honour the B. Sacrament, that they might litle think their doctrine savourd of Calvinisme. They were to extoll one another: to profess themselves to be knowing men, &amp; to gaine the reputation of being great schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, &amp; for this end, were to talk much in the pulpit &amp; in company, of Predestination, of grace, &amp; of Saint Austin; yet when they met with thos that were learneder then themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, they were to be very reserved in declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their opinions; &amp; if they did, they were to do it in forme of a bare narrative, and in case they were required to explicate themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, they were to cry out, <hi>O altitudo, &amp;c.</hi> or say that S. Austin is very plain in the case, &amp; then to fall a praysing the Holy Doctor, that less notice might be taken of the sense of his words: When they spoke of the charmes &amp; sweatnes of victorious grace, they were to adde, that it was to be known by certain marks, that are not given to all; Yet were they not presently to describe thes markes, but only to say, that they are given to thos
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172251:10"/>that are capable of them, for this would be the infallible way, to draw people to a longing desire, to consult with them about the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant affayrs of their salvation, &amp; then they should not want an occasion to instil the principles of their doctrine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="means">
                  <head>The fift Meanes. <hi>To gain seculars, &amp; engage them to their Partie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Being thus prepared, they bent all their thoughts and endeavours, to find favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Catholiks, and despairing to get it but of the Clergy or Laity, they did their best to gain both; &amp; first the <hi>Prelats, Curats &amp; simple Priests,</hi> by thes meanes: Giving every one of them all possible honour according to his degree: Often praysing them, yet without affectation: Extolling their caracters, dignities, &amp; functions: Obligingly &amp; with zeal of their glory, insinuating the obligation which God has layd vpon them, to governe soules, to reforme the present conduct of the Church, to give a lustre to the Ecclesiastical state, &amp; to depress Religious, who by their spiritual direction, have entrenched vpon the right &amp; practise of the secular Clergy: Encouraging them to Sermons, Catechisms,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172251:11"/>&amp; spiritual conferences, to get the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of knowing &amp; devout men: Setting a high valew vpon their Books &amp; direction, to draw the people after them inculcating in their Books, Sermons, &amp; private discourses, that the people are bound, to be directed in their consciences by secular Priests: Casting a scruple vpon thos that suffer themselves to be directed by Religious persons: Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that all disorders amongst Christians, have proceeded from the inverting this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; bringing plausible proofs of it from the ancient government of the Church, to persuade the world, that their only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is to reestablish it: Offering relief to those that are in need of it: In fine leading them according to their predominant inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the noble &amp; learned by honour &amp; glory the ambitious by dignities, the poor &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous by pensions, the fervent &amp; zealous by reformation of manners. In a word profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to all, a great passion for their spiritual &amp; temporal advantages.</p>
                  <p>Besides all thes meanes, they fell vpon a design of setting vp assemblies of Priests, to teach them the ceremonies of the divine offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the administration of Sacraments, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of a spiritual life, &amp; way of directing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences; &amp; withall to instill their new doctrin,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172251:11"/>craftily mingled with things so holy and so profitable.</p>
                  <p>Having thus agreed vpon the way, how to conquer the secular Clergy, which they allways esteemed a matter of highest concern, not only because the flock of Christ would easily fall into their snares, but also because the Pastors being once corrupted, would of themselves lead their sheep to the wolves that seek to devour them: They fell vpon the means how to draw in the Laity.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore they resolved to gain the esteem of the <hi>Great ones</hi> by their elaborare &amp; commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious sermons; by their sweet &amp; polish'd lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, by their curious &amp; winning conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the repute of men wel versed in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, in the holy Fathers, &amp; in the Maximes of a good Moral: by opinions differing from the common strain, but not altogether, new: by a thousand testimonies of honour, &amp; a world of curtesies vpon all occasions: &amp; by taking still their measures according to the present circumstances &amp; every ones nature, &amp; interest, praysing or reprehending, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving or rejecting, &amp; pvtting on all sorts of persons, according to the rules of a most exact complaisance.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Ladies,</hi> they were persuaded, that the way to insinuate themselves into their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172251:12"/>favour, was by modesty and sweetnes: by a pritty effeminate kind of way in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: by neat &amp; proper language: by devout sighs: by often casting vp their eys towards heaven: by an extraordinary kind of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dressed vp in a n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w phrase: by Books cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously bound: by discourses of Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, liberty &amp; grace, by a moderate and wel managed ostentation of a new secret, to guide souls, vnknown to other Confessors &amp; Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors: by visits contrived to please their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours: by marks of an entier and pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne for their sanctification: by slighting as it were by chance all Confessors, Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours &amp; spiritual Books, that are not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their model and conduct: by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual yealding to their inclinations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are commonly taken with the love, esteem, honour, prays &amp; observance which men give them.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>People,</hi> they did not question but modesty, short hayre, litle bands, moderate sleeves, long cloakes, long &amp; frequent prayers in the Church stately ceremonies in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin Office, great almes, severe penances, bitter invectives against the softnes of their first Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectours: in a word all that exteriour beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour which caries the caracter of a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, would soon gain their approbation, &amp; a tendernes of hart for their new opinions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="means">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:172251:12"/>
                  <head>The sixt Meanes <hi>To treat differently with persons of different natures &amp; dispositions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Though thes generall means are very much to the purpose, yet they cannot serve all sorts of persons. For some are suspected not to be wel affected to new opinions: others are simple &amp; sincere: others indifferent, declaring for neither side: others fervent and devout: others indevout and mere libertins: wherfore with great prudence &amp; dexterity, they fitted their policy accordingly, that it might serve for all sorts of dispositions, &amp; thus they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne themselves.</p>
                  <p>With <hi>Suspected persons.</hi> 1. They deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be Iansenists, &amp; disown the new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, when they deal with thos that have a horrour of it. 2. They declare their opinion in such tearmes, as make it not much differ from the common opinion, that they may gain them by degrees. 3. when they grant that God gives graces to the reprobate, that have no effect, they forbear to declare whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be or be not, for want of their coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with such graces. 4. They cry vp the name of liberty, &amp; do not say that grace puts a necessity vpon the will: but only say, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172251:13"/>victorious grace carries away the will sweetly, without constraint or violence, which is true according to their meaning, because they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a liberty which is only opposite to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint. But their equivocation consists in this, that they meane, that victorious grace forces the will by an antecedent necessity. 5. They never meddle with Propositions that sound harshly, as that Christ died not for all men, that Gods Commandements are impossible &amp;c. But they speak only of Predestination, victorious grace &amp;c. as if thes were the only questions; because from thes they easily draw their other opinions. 6. They profess to be men of peace, &amp; to grieve at the scandal, which is caused by thes disputes, &amp; they far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declare; that ther ought to be no preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or writing on either side.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVith thos that are Simple,</hi> who having no great reach seek only their salvation. 1. They deal with them, much as they do with suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed persons. 2 When they convers with them, they are attentive to discover what effects they work in their brains. 3. And if they find in them, the least affection to novelty they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their doctrine as new, at least to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Church, Scholastical diuins and some Councils since S. Austin. 4. They give them or lend them Books, which insinuate, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172251:13"/>their doctrine. 5. They employ wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; secular girles, that love change and variety, to draw men to their sentiments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVith Neutrals,</hi> 1. They treat them as suspected. 2. They convay Books &amp; writings into their houses that their own curiosity may invite them, to receave instruction, which they cannot so conveniently communicate by word of month. 3. They conceal their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to stir vp their curiosity, 4. With thos that leane to their side, they freely declare themselves against their adversaries, whom they miscal Molinists, Pelagians &amp; Semipela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVith thos that are fervent &amp; devout;</hi> They teach, that the only solid devotion is that of S. Austin, to have a colour to introduce their novelties: That the chief thing which makes a pious action, grateful in the sight of God, is grace, without which, the best workes are sinfull. That pride often corrups the best a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. That it is the height of pride to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, we have any part in devout actions, which God works in vs; and that we can merit by them. That a mans greatest vertu &amp; glory, is to hould himself so depending of grace, that it do all things in vs &amp; without vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVith indevout &amp; Libertin soules.</hi> They tell them, that God from all eternity, has deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172251:14"/>our salvation &amp; damnation. That we cannot alter this decree. That Religious auste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and mortifications torture them to no purpose: That the Council of Trent which teaches the contrary, was not oecumenical, but was made vp of Monkes: That the Janse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists are the learnedest and best wits: That God died not for all, nor for the reprobate: That he gives them no grace, not so much as sufficient: That all grace is efficacious, &amp; vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, without our cooperation: That when we have once receaved this grace, it is a sign of our Predestination, &amp; a cause of great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="means">
                  <head>The seventh Meanes. <hi>To set vp Communities of men &amp; women, &amp; to keep private Pensioners.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Casting their thoughts vpon times to come, they prudently judged nothing more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; more efficacious, to give a lasting being to any design, that is once set on foot, then to erect Congregations of men &amp; Communities of women. Because the doctrine, conduct, manners &amp; inclinations of the first founders, is derived successfully into all their followers, as we see by experience, of many ages, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious orders. Wherfore they convayd their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172251:14"/>sentiments &amp; principles, into a Congregation of Priests, who, for all they labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade the contrary, have a hard task to purge themselves, and into the Monastery of the Nuns of Port-royal who will not be disabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. They have also procured (vnder pretence of reforming the Clergy) the establishment of divers Communities of Priests, since the year 1640. &amp; Seminaries, for the Instruction of those that are to take Holy Orders. But because they had just reason to think, that all thos that were bred in such Communities, would not be drawn to their doctrine, but that the greatest part, would stick close to their Catholike principles, or would not be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that secrecy; which they required: they contented themselves, to keep there certain Pensioners, such as they took to be discreet, faithful, &amp; zealous for their Partie; that thes, by their prudent dissimulation, might instill an esteem of their particular opinions, &amp; a hatred against Religious persons, their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test adversaries. Which succeeded so happily, that we hardly find a Priest, that has been bred in such Communities, who is not an enemy to Regulars. Even thos that are cald <hi>Devotes,</hi> are infected with this venome, and publish without scruple, <hi>that the spirit of God has deserted Religious persons.</hi> With the like success, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172251:15"/>gave Pensions to certain Officers, and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticks of the Prelats, to rule them at their pleasure. To prebends &amp; heads of Chapters: to thos that had any eminent talent to write, or preach, or convers, or teach in Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or private Colleges: to all thos in fine, that could introduce their doctrine, into the Courts of Justice, Courts of Princes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Great ones. This contrivance of theirs, has wonderfully spread their errours, because it sutes wel with mens inclinations, who are much set vpon temporal goods.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="means">
                  <head>The eighth Meanes. <hi>To have a common purse &amp; to gather great almes for their common charges.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>But considering, that vast summs of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, were requisite for so many pensions, &amp; for printing Books, &amp; other necessary char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they resolved, to make the richest of their partie, pay contribution (as the Calvinists do so luckily to this day) &amp; to draw what almes they could, from all that suffered themselves to be guided by them. To this purpose, they collected out of Scripture &amp; holy Fathers, all the best arguments, to persuade that rich men, have an indispensable obligation, to give
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172251:15"/>great almes. To this they added the examples of Saints, that gave all they had to the poor, &amp; the advantages which Christians, &amp; chiefly Penitents &amp; new Converts, gather by it, to satisfy Gods Justice, &amp; purchase an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary degree of sanctity, &amp; with much elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; they held forth all the arguments they could invent. And because they meant, in pursuance of their project, to have the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of this mony, they gave out, that the best almes, and most pleasing to God, were thos that were the most secret. This made them trusted, with so considerable summs of mony, that they have hetherto lived at a vast rate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="means">
                  <head>The ninth Meanes. <hi>To make Apologies to defend themselves, &amp; abuse their adversaries.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Their doctrine being against the faith of the Church, they did not question but it would be generally opposed. If their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were Bishops, or great persons, they thought it best to be quiet, &amp; not to stir in the matter, but to play out of sight, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themselves to dispose persons by degrees. If they were of a meaner condition, &amp; would not be gaind by their devices, they took it to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172251:16"/>be lawfull, to make a strict enquiry into their lives; to threaten to ruine their reputation &amp; fortunes, &amp; to do it actually, yet warily, &amp; with the advice of all their known followers. In fine they judged it requisite, in case they were assaulted, eyther in their persons or in their doctrine, to have recourse to Apologies, for by that meanes, they would gaine a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advantage, not only of beating down their adversaries, but of raysing their trophies on their ruins, not only of making them passe for Pelagians &amp; Semipelagians, but of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own opinions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="means">
                  <head>The tenth Meanes. <hi>To ruin the reputation &amp; authority of Religious.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Now amongst all their enemies, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended none so much as Regulars. They considered, that in all ages, they were the men, that had the happines, to defend the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox faith, against Hereticks: That they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all Christians, had the greatest inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, in the conservation of Religion, &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Monarchy: That embracing the severest Maximes of the Ghospel, &amp; the most eminent vertues of Christianity, they are for the most part, very zealous, for the true faith:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172251:16"/>That being disengaged from secular affairs, &amp; having their time and spare houres appointed for the study of Divine Sciences, they are commonly fitter to encounter with novelties then men of the world, That they make vp bodies, that are immortal, &amp; that hand down the same spirit from age to age, &amp; are disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed all over christerdome, &amp; so can preach &amp; write in all languages, &amp; in all times &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, against all heresies whatsoever: That they rule the consciences, of the greatest part of Christians, who are therfore guided by their counsel &amp; doctrine: That it is impossible to draw them, at least all, to embrace their sect the Superiours, &amp; even inferiours, who are zealous, for the Church, having their eys open, to discover the carriage &amp; sentiments of their Brothers: That they have power in the Court of Rome, &amp; with Kings &amp; Princes, &amp; can luckily vnite the Ecclesiastical &amp; secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar power, to destroy Novelties. From thes evident &amp; convincing reasons, they conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it was absolutly necessary, to destroy Regulars, &amp; without remedy to ruin their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation &amp; functions, in the Church of JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS-<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>HRIST. And that as they write, in their Circular Letter, to the Disciples of S. Austin. <hi>If the Founder of the Calvinists, had not beaten down the monks pride, &amp; set vpon the racking doctrine of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172251:17"/>works of supererogation &amp; merits, which brings in their dayly bread, he would never have established himself, so luckily as he did, &amp; therfore they were to follow the same track.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now to compasse this vndertaking, they all agreed in this; That they were to draw the people, from having so much confidence in Religious persons, by persuading them, that they live not according to their rules: That their manners are corrupted: that their dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is hurtful to soules: That their doctrine is erroneous, in point of Predestination, &amp; Grace: That they brought into the Church, the abuses that are practised: That they slight Priests &amp; Parishes: That they have vsurped the direction of Consciences, &amp; the Office of preaching, which belongs to secular Priests: That they belong not to the Ecclesiastical Hierarchy: That they are vain, worldly, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, &amp; full of revenge: That though they profess to ayme at Gods glory, in the excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their functions, yet they wrest it to their own interest, in abominable things.</p>
                  <p>To give thes arguments more force, they resolved to gather together, (as they have done) all that has been written, to dishonour Religious, that they may serve themselves of it, vpon occasions: To destroy in the harts of the people, that veneration which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172251:17"/>in stiling them Fathers: To annihilate the doctrine of works of supererogation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they take it to be their greatest support, &amp; chiefest ground of their subsistance: To convince secular Priests, that the Religious labour for nothing more, then to keep them down, as the scumm &amp; scorn of the people: To vnite Priests in one body, to oppose Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, &amp; reserve to themselves the direction of soules, &amp; the office of preaching, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, &amp; Missions: To cry down before Prelats, their Privileges &amp; exemption: In fine to sow jealousies, &amp; divisions amongst them, to fight them, &amp; overthrow them, with their own weapons.</p>
                  <p>Yet for all the success, which they promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed themselves, from thes wel contrived meanes; they were absolutly persuaded, that all would do nothing, so long as the Jesuists were in being; The reasons were thes. They teach most of the youth in Christendome: They almost alone, furnish Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with Novices, for when do you see any leave the Oratorians, or other secular Priests Colleges, to enter into Monasteries: They have the way to beat into their Schollars, the principles of faith &amp; Catholike verities, so that it is very hard to pervert them: Lastly by their Books, Sermons, schollars, Direction,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172251:18"/>Missions, &amp; all their Religious &amp; spiritual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, they have got so illustrious a reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to have the credit, of conserving the people in Catholike Religion. To all this they added, that thes Religious, make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, to oppose hereticks tooth &amp; nail, &amp; chiefly modern, who at present, are not a litle incommoded by them. Which forced the Abbot Saint Cyran, to pronounce this judgment against them. <hi>That it is wholly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to destroy them, to establish S. Austins</hi> (that is as I noted) <hi>Calvins, doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To compass this, which imports them so much, for the accomplishment of their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther designs: They fell presently to write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Schools, against their Masters &amp; manner of teaching. They layd trading to their charge, &amp; other things, which seemd sufficient, to make them odious to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; They did their best, to set other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous against them: They vsed all their cunning, to discredite their Books, their Preachers, their devines, all their Authors, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, &amp; spiritual conduct. The falsnes of thes imputation, being soon discovered, to the dishonour of the accusers, they had recours to the subtle Policy of the Minister du Moulin. This spirit, as rich in inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as in drollery, heretofore made a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172251:18"/>of the largest opinions of Catholike Casuists, to persuade his followers that the doctrine of the Roman Church, was naught and corrupted. The Jansenists have in like manner, &amp; with incredible cunning, written against the Jesuists Moral &amp; though knowing men, who have searched their Books, the better to judge of the Jansenists sincerity or forgery, have discovered their false dealing, and strange impostures: yet the people in Towns, wher the Jesuits neyther dwel nor converse, have been persuaded that their Morall is corrupted, &amp; their spiritual direction too condescending. The Prelats themselves, &amp; the Curates, whether out of envy or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, have much concurred with the Janse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, to atchieve this enterprize, &amp; to this day, some of them, can not hould from shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their teeth against them. With such Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, have thes new Hereticks, engaged in their concernes, even thos that should have protected them, the better to stifle the rising heresy of Jansenius.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="means">
                  <head>The eleventh Meanes. <hi>To elude the condemnation of their Heresies, by the three senses, &amp; by the Question of Right &amp; Fact, &amp; by foisting in their doctrine, in the Translations, of some workes of the Holy Fathers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172251:19"/>
                  <p> God is ever so watchful over his Church, that all the Jansenists artifices, could not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Popes, Innocent X. &amp; Alexander VII. from condemning their errours. Wherfore being resolved, according to their fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal maxime, to live exteriorly in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Catholike Church, they were constrained, to avoid the fury of the Vatican thunderbolts, levelled against them, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving recourse to their ordinary shifts. First they found out 3. <hi>senses,</hi> to the Propositions condemned by his Holines, and maintaind that they were not condemned in Jansenius his sense, to wipe off from him, as wel as from themselves, the foul blot of heresy, and to conserve thos they had already drawn to their Partie, who were vpon the point of deserting them.</p>
                  <p>But this first defence, being quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, by Alexander VII. his Constitution, they wisely started the Question of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Fact,</hi> granting the Pope infallibility, to judg &amp; define matters of Right in points of faith, but not matters of <hi>Fact.</hi> So that they are content, to condemn &amp; receave for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Propositions vnderstood in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural sense, in whatsoever Authors they are to be found, but they affirm, that they are not in Jansenius his Book, &amp; that the Popes er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in that.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:172251:19"/>
                  <p> To strengthen this second defence, they raisd vp the Sect of the Richerists, of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, against the Popes infallibility in points of faith, when they are joynd with matter of <hi>Fact.</hi> They also endevoured, to render his spiritual jurisdiction over the whol Church, suspected to Soveraigns, &amp; odious to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vsing fals &amp; captious reasons, to persuade them, that he meant by degrees, to vsurp a Soveraignty, over the temporal right of Kings &amp; Princes.</p>
                  <p>But not daring at present, openly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, or publish their opinions, after they have been so solemnly condemned by the Church, they found out a subtle peece of Policy, to translate into French, certain Peeces of the Holy Fathers, which seem to favour them, and ther cunningly to foist in their condemned propositions, that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may swallow them without reflexion, &amp; that thos who vnderstand neyther Greek, nor Latin, may believe, that thos Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, held the Jansenists tenets. The learned &amp; judicious Author, of the Letters to an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bess of Cistaux, has discovered this new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp; by his just censures, has prevented the bad consequences.</p>
                  <p>Sir, if you take the paines, to observe attentively, the admirable Policy of thes No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velists,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172251:20"/>I am confident, you will cease to wonder, that they have so easily cheated, so many Catholiks in France &amp; other places, &amp; that it is so hard a thing, for a man to keep out of their nets, and not to turn heretick when he thinks to become a good Christian, by the help of their direction.</p>
                  <p>But whatsoever they have done, to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish their doctrine, nothing has succeeded so luckily as in the Sorbon, where having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the Readers of divinity, with their new fancies, they easily spread their poyson all over the Kingdome.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE PRESENT STATE OF THE SORBON. OF PARIS.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>TO MONSIEVR LE CHEVALIER</hi> DES TROISPONTS.</head>
               <p>To prove that which I was saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the SORBON is infected with Iansenisme,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is necessary to fetch the matter a litle higher.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proof">
                  <head>THE FIRST PROOF. <hi>VVhich serves for Introduction, to thos that follow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172251:20"/>
                  <p> I Beseech you Sir to observe, that in the year 1611. Cornelius Jansenius a Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Bishop of Ipers in Flanders, &amp; John de Havane de Verger, of Bayonne, afterwards Abbot of S. Cyran, in Berry, layd the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their frendship, &amp; contrived their design, which they afterwards labourd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, one in the University of Lovain, the other in that of Paris. This last, drew im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to his partie, the three Arnauds his Brothers, viz Monsieur d'Andilly, the Doctour, &amp; the Abbot of S. Nicholas, now Bishop of Angiers. Besides Monsieur le Maistre, Advocate of the Parliament, their Nephew; their Sisters, Nuns of Port-royal, &amp; many yong Bachelers &amp; Doctours, amongst whom, I was one, as zealous as the rest, drawn in by the novelty of their doctrine.</p>
                  <p>This plague, which stole secretly into mens minds, broke out at last, &amp; became so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, vnder the pretended autority of Saint Austin, that Monsieur S. Beuve, Professour of Divinity, deliverd it to his Schollars, in his dictates and publick lessons. Thus the Jansenists began, to corrupt the Sorbon Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in its very source. And as water, which flowes from a poisoned fountain, carries the deadly poyson along with it; so we retain the first instructions, we receave from our masters.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172251:21"/>And vsually men keep, the first impression, they took in their youth, &amp; strictly tye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to the first principles they learnt, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when the contrary principles, are cried down, for false &amp; ridiculous, &amp; this in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning Religion: When the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of such doctrine, condemn their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries of great failings, which must cause lamentable consequences: When they are persuaded that such pretended truths, are the very same, which the Holy Ghost has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veald in Holy Scripture, &amp; declared in the workes of the Holy Fathers: And besides, that thos that embrace them, have the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of able, witty, curious, &amp; charming men in their conversation. Then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention which followes with their Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, stirs vp their industry &amp; ambition, to defend their novelties, &amp; kindles a hatred to their enemies, which inflames their false zeal. The applause of their friends, which goes still encreasing gives them new courage. In fine the hope to make their names immortal, for having raysd a famous dispute in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, between the old Catholicks and new Sectaries. Thes reasons me thought, were so strong &amp; convincing, that I do not wonder, that eyther I, or my Schoolfellows enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. And that this is the vsual way, which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172251:21"/>Novellists take, to seduce Catholicks, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin affords me an argument, very pat for my purpose. Being returned out of Germany, into France, he retired himself to Bourges, about the year 1533. and began to preach at Asnieres, a country Town about a league &amp; a half distant from that City, which still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the heresy he then planted. Having the out side of a wel behaved Priest, as the Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senists have now for the most part, he easily gaind the frendship &amp; confidence of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of yong Ecclesiasticks, &amp; he so deeply stampt his errours in their soules, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of reforming their manners, &amp; teaching them the new secrets of a spiritual life, that some years after being condemned by the Church, all but the ancientest amongst them, vndertook the defence of his opinions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused the Pope of injustice, and in fine fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him to Geneva. Had the Abbot of S. Cyran, the Arnauds, le Maistre &amp; S. Beuve, taken their flight to Geneva, as wel as they followed the doctrine of Geneva, I know not whether their Schollars in the Sorbon, would have followed them, but this I know that they faithfully follow their Masters opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. Thos that are not so certain of it, as I am, will be convinced, by the following Proofs, which I draw from the exact agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they have with the Jansenists.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proof">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:172251:22"/>
                  <head>The second Proof.</head>
                  <p>First who knows not, that the Jansenists teach heresy, since their doctrine has been condemned for heretical, &amp; their Books for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden as Luthers &amp; Calvins were? It is also true, that the new Sorbonists, approve, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, &amp; protect their errours. Monsieur R. who goes vnder the name of Montalte; speaks it plainly, in his first Provincial Letter, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. of the Colen Edition 1657. in thes termes. When Monsieur Arnauds second Letter, was examined in the Sorbon <hi>three score &amp; eleven Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, stood vp for him.</hi> And in his third Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>pag.</hi> 37. The examiners <hi>were by this means,</hi> says he, <hi>freed from the importunity of thes trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Doctors, who took a pleasure to refute all their reasons, &amp; to produce Books to convince them of falshood, To summon them to answear, &amp; to force them to a non plus.</hi> And a litle after, he goes on thus <hi>They are sufficiently persuaded, that thos that are in their wits, will make more of the judgment of the</hi> 70. <hi>Doctors, who could get nothing by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Monsieur Arnaud, then of</hi> 100 <hi>others, who had nothing to loos by condemning him.</hi> Now if threescore &amp; eleven Doctors, defend Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Arnauds heresies, who is now the head of the Jansenists: If they defend them in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172251:22"/>most famous Assemblies of the Sorbon: If they quote Authors to maintain them: If they bring arguments to confirme them, &amp; refute the contrary arguments, so farr as to pretend to convince their adversaries of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood, &amp; put them to silence: Is it not easy to conclude, that they are wholly addicted to thes heresies? that they are obstinately tied to them? that they espouse them for their own proper doctrine? Especially since they had rather, expose themselves to the Popes curses, &amp; the Kings indignation, who commands them to be censured, then to quit them, &amp; permit the sound part of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon to condemn them.</p>
                  <p>Of this number are the five Doctors, whom Montalte in his first Letter <hi>pag.</hi> 3. cals <hi>Indifferent,</hi> for if they stood not for the Catholicks they were consequently for the Jansenists: For ther is no neutrality in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: It is Christ JESVS his infallible word. <hi>He that is not with him is against him:</hi> Ther is no midle way to walk in, between Faith, &amp; articles directly opposite to Faith. Why then did not the pretended <hi>Indifferents,</hi> side with the Clergy, the King, the Pope, the whol Church, to defend the Faith, according to the obligation of their oath, as they are Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, but because they were mislead by the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172251:23"/>Jansenists? So that if we reckon wel with Montalte, behold 86. Sorbon Doctors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Jansenisme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proof">
                  <head>The third Proof.</head>
                  <p>Secondly; They approved the Jansenists Books which contain errours against faith. It is easy to prove it by examples. Witnes the Book of Virginity, which Father Segue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not an Oratorian, writ against Religious vowes. Which made Cardinal Richelieu (who was certainly the true defender of the Faith) to cast him into the Bastile; wher he also layd the Abbot of S. Cyran. Monsieur Gerbais &amp; A. Favre Doctors of Sorbon, on the 14. of Apr. 1663. approved the Book of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Masse; written by Monsieur Steven Guerry, Doctour of Divinity, &amp; Curate of S. Opportune in Poitiers printed at Niort by Francis Bouhault 1664. which teaches, <hi>pag.</hi> 200. <hi>that Curates are of divine Institution, &amp; have the same authority in their Parishes, which the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe has over the whol Church, or the Bishops in their Dioceses.</hi> (So they would have equal authority with the Bishops and Pope himself: is that true?) <hi>pag.</hi> 203. <hi>That the Curates cannot be outed by the Pope, their state being equally essential to the Church. That they are as essentially members, as the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172251:23"/>Pope is head of the Church.</hi> And yet Popes have deposed Bishops, are Curates more indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant? Besides if the Primacy, and Caracter of the Pope, were destroyd, we should not haue the same Church, because Christ insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted her vnder a visible head, his Lieutenant vpon earth; but if ther were no Curates, would she therfore be destroyd? <hi>pag.</hi> 208. <hi>That the Parochial Church Alone, is the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted by Iesus Christ, for the learning the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Ghospel, &amp; vse of the Sacraments.</hi> The Pope then and the Bishops cannot permit them in other Churches. Do Catholike Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors agree in this?</p>
                  <p>Monsieur Grenet &amp; N. Petitpied 6. Octob. 1663. approved the Translation of many of S. Bernards Sermons, corrupted by the Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senists in 2. severall passages, in favour of their heresies. The first is <hi>pag.</hi> 138. §. 6. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon 20. <hi>Erat</hi> (says the holy Father) <hi>totâ ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ doctus, sed adhuc infirmus; benè instructus, sed parum adjutus.</hi> Speaking of Saint Peter, <hi>his soul was sul of knowledge to love Christ, but he was we<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k in that love, he was wel instructed but litle helped.</hi> The translatour says, <hi>he wanted not knowlege but wanted help,</hi> wher thes last words <hi>he wanted help,</hi> contain the heresy condemned in one of the 5. Propositions, &amp; censured in Arnauds second Letter. 1656. The second is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172251:24"/>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 38. <hi>Sermon</hi> 30. in the beginning. <hi>Est cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas in actu, est &amp; in affectu: Et de illa quidem quae operis est, puto datam esse legem hominibus mandatum{que} formatum. Nam in affectu quis ita habeat vt mandatur? Ther is a charity,</hi> says the Jansenist, <hi>which lies in the affection, &amp; another which consists in the action: &amp; I believe it is for the first, that a law was given vnto men, &amp; a commandment drawn out of it. For who can have the other in that perfection which the law requires.</hi> This Translation is fals and rayses heresies. 1. It changes S. Bernards order, who puts charity of action in the first place, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of affection in the second. 2. From this disorder, which the Translatour makes, it followes that the command for charity of action, is impossible, and consequently that ther are some of Gods commandements, that are impossible, which is condemned in one of the 5. Propositions.</p>
                  <p>Monsieur Boisleau &amp; A. Favre 11. Apr. &amp; 2. Iul. 1664. approved the book of Faith touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Eucharist, &amp; yet the Authour, who is thought to be Monsieur Arnaud, makes S. Austin speak a horrible heresy It is in the <hi>pag.</hi> 118. which begins thus, <hi>connoissent tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clairement,</hi> in the impression of Savreux 1664. <hi>It is</hi> says he, <hi>in the power of men to sinn (says S. Austin) but it is not in their power, to commit
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172251:24"/>such or such a sinn. It is God that rules thos which he ought to permit, &amp; thos which he ought to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ordering darknes:</hi> See the words taken out of his Book of the Predestination of Saints Chap. 16. <hi>Est ergo in potestate malorum peccare: Vt autem peccando, hoc vel hoc illâ malitiâ fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant, non est in eorum potestate, sed Dei dividen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; ordinantis tenebras.</hi> That is. <hi>It is therfore in the power of the wicked to sinn; but that in sinning they do this or that, by this malice, it is not in their power, but in Gods who divides &amp; orders darknes.</hi> This holy Father, speakes only of the effects, which follow out of the sins of the wicked, &amp; says, that God disposes of thes effects, to draw out the good, which pleases him. The Author of the <hi>Perpetuity</hi> makes him say, that God rules or determins mens sins: and besides that <hi>it is not in their power to commit such or such a sinn.</hi> So that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to him, God must give this power: wherfore he makes God the Authour of sinn as Calvin did before him.</p>
                  <p>I omitt other pernicious Books, which they have approved, &amp; draw this conclusion. When the Sorbonists approved the Jansenists Books, they knew their errours: for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not suppose ignorance in such great Doctors: They did not approve them as Catholike Doctors, for they ought rather to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172251:25"/>them: Therfore they approved them as Jansenian Doctors. Ther is no middle between as I have proved. If the Doctors of Sorbon answear, that all the Doctors of their Faculty, did not give thos approbations, I answear, that they seemed to give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, otherwise they should have disowned &amp; condemned Arnaud &amp; S. Beuve, nay more degraded them from being Doctors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proof">
                  <head>The fourth Proof.</head>
                  <p>In the third place: They have not censured Books &amp; Translations, in which the Janse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, have cunningly delivered their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies. It shall suffice to quote four amongst many others, which they have spared. The first is the Houres or Prayers, which have been printed 15. or 16. times, though cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured at Rome: &amp; wher thes Hereticks, have dashed out of the Hymns, JESVS CHRISTS title, of Redeemer of all men. They have translated the verse of the Psalm. 138. <hi>Mihi autem nimis honorificati sunt amici tui Deus: nimis confortatus est principatus eorum,</hi> according to Beza's translation, printed at Sedan 1623. <hi>O how pretious are thy counsels vnto me,</hi> says that Heretick: <hi>O how hard a thing it is to summ them vp, for if I would rekcon them all, they will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172251:25"/>exceed in number the sands on the shore.</hi> And the Jansenists <hi>pag.</hi> 199. <hi>O Almighty God,</hi> say they, <hi>how the sublimity of thy thoughts is precious vnto me, &amp; how immense their number apears to me? if I would count them, they appear more innumerable then the sands of the sea.</hi> They left this transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church and Holy Fathers <hi>(Thy friends o God are made wonderfully honourable vnto me, their principality is greatly confirmed)</hi> because it serves to prove the honour, which Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks give to the blessed Saints.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 332. They renew some of the 5. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Propositions, when they say, <hi>VVe offer thee</hi> (God) <hi>our prayers, that thou wilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> (men of whom he speakes) <hi>by the invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible force of thy Spirit, to which no liberty of men can make resistance, when thou wilt love them.</hi> Which words have the same sense with thes others: <hi>That we never resist interiour grace, that liberty is not free from necessity, but only from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint: that God has an absolute will, antecedent to the consent of the will of a man predestinate, &amp; that he puts a necessity vpon him to consent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To seduce the Reader they attribute thes heresies to S. Austin in his 4. Book to Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, Chap. 9. who says no such matter, hear his words. <hi>Quid ergo petimus, nisi vt fiant ex nolentibus volentes, ex repugnantibus consentientes, ex oppugnantibus amantes? A quo, nisi ab illo de quo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172251:26"/>scriptum est: praeparatur voluntas à Deo? Discant ergo esse Catholici, qui dedignantur, si quid mali non faciunt &amp; si quid boni faciunt, non in se ipsis, sed in Domino gloriari. What do we aske then, but that of vnwilling they become willing, of resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing consenting, of oppugning loving? By whom but by him, of whom it is written, the will is prepared by God? Let them therfore learn to be Catholicks, who scorn to glorify themselves, not in themselves, but in our Lord, if they do nothing that is ill, &amp; do somthing that is good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The second is Montalts Letters to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial: This jesting spirit makes the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Arnauds second Letter, about suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Grace, &amp; principles of Morality, to be ridiculous, and scatters many heresies all over his Book, which was condemned at Rome 6. Sept. 1657, &amp; burnt by the decree of the Parliament of Aix. The third is, the summary of the Curates declarations &amp;c. by M. John Rousse Doctor &amp; Curate in Paris, censured at Rome 30. June 1659. The fourth is the Collection of divers peeces, about the Censures of the Faculty of Paris, printed at Munster 1666. full of heresies, &amp; invectives against the Pope, as we shal see below, &amp; condemned to the fire, by a decree of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 17. May. 1666.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place. They have quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172251:26"/>censured Catholicke Books, written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Jansenists. For proof of this, I will only bring Monsieur Jacques Vernant, who defends the Popes spiritual authority, against the errours of the times: by formal texts out of Scripture out of the first general Councils of the Church, out of the Holy Fathers, &amp; Orthodox Doctors: &amp; by arguments of good divinity; And all this, with so great solidity, clearnes, &amp; fidelity in his citations, that ther is no rational man, that will not be convinced of the truth.</p>
                  <p>After thes observations, I demand, why the Sorbonists, who make profession to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure Books, contrary to faith &amp; good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, have nevertheles omitted Books and Translations corrupted by the Jansenists? They must eyther be their friends, or their enemies, or neutrals: They are not their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for were they so they would beat down their heresies, with a thousand censures: They are not neutrals, for that cannot be, ther being as I sayd, no neutrality to be found, between the true faith &amp; heresy. And truly, if they were so, they would not approve their Books, as they have done, nor treat their Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries works so ill. Wherfore they are their friends. And truly perfect friendship (says S. Hierom excellently wel) engages men to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172251:27"/>will and not to will the same things: <hi>Eadem velle &amp; eadem nolle, ea demum firma amicitia est. Epist. ad Demetriad</hi> She also inspires (as Saint Chrysostome speaks) a sollicitous care of knowing the frends concerns, carries a man with zeal, to maintain their interest. In fine it is her nature, to do them all the good she can possibly, &amp; not to suffer any, to do them the least mischief. <hi>Qui amant, ii plus quàm cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri omnes eorum facta norunt, vt qui de iis ipsis sint solliciti. S. Chrysost. praefat. in Epist. S. Pauli.</hi> Do not the Sorbonists religiously observe the laws of a perfect freindship? Have not they generously obliged the Jansenists, in their head Arnaud, as we have seen in Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talts letters, quoted in my second Proof? Besides since frendship easily engages vs in the same hatred, which our friends have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their enemies, &amp; consequently vnites our designs, and forces, to fight and destroy them, ought we not to Confess, that the Sorbonists are straightly tied to the Jansenists, &amp; that they have the same designs, since, as we have seen, they vnanimously fight their enemies in censuring Catholike Books writt against them? <hi>Quales amicos quisque habet, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem scias,</hi> sayd an Ancient Author.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proof">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:172251:27"/>
                  <head>The fift Proof.</head>
                  <p>To strengthen this Proof, I adde another agreement between the Sorbonists. Thes seek to pul down Soveraign Bishops, by raising two heads vpon the Throne of the Church, by despizing their constitutions, by questioning their infallibility in decisions of Faith, &amp; by publishing a thousand calumnies against them. The Sorbonists have also declared themselves the Popes enemies, &amp; given many proofs of their hatred. Take the first from their propositions concerning his authority. I only instance in the sixt, by which they rob the Pope of the infallibility, which CHRIST gave him in deciding matters of Faith. <hi>It is not,</hi> say they, <hi>the doctrin or opinion of the Faculty, that the Chief Bishop is infallible, vnles the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Church be joyned with it.</hi> In this they agree with the Jansenists. The second is drawn from their Censure of Monsieur Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants brok. This Orthodox Catholik teaches 1. that the Pope is infallible in deciding mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith. <hi>Epist. Dedic. &amp; pag.</hi> 254. 2. That no authority vnder God, can limit his power. <hi>pag.</hi> 110.3. That were he not infallible in matters of Faith, we ought to give over say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that we believe in the holy Catholick &amp;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172251:28"/>Apostolick Roman Church. <hi>pag.</hi> 247. 4. That the Decrees of Gen. Councils, ought to have the Popes approbation, because they do not receave their jurisdiction immediately from God, but at the hands of S. Peter, &amp; his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours. <hi>pag.</hi> 358. 721. 724. 5. That the Pope is the supreme judge of all greater cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses or questions of Faith, &amp; that ther is no appeal from his judgment. <hi>pag.</hi> 100. 244. 279. 428. 6. That JESVS CHRIST, gave S. Peter &amp; his Successors, all that authority, which he had receaved from his Father, for the government of the Church, in things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the sayd government. <hi>pag.</hi> 53. 128. 143. 145. 7, That the Pope can delegate his jurisdiction, &amp; part it as he pleases, in Pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral functions, in the Dioceses of all Bishops without asking their consent. <hi>pag.</hi> 365. 366. The Sorbonists call the first of thes proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, temerarious, scandalous, heretical. The 2. fals. The 3. fals, temerarious, scandalous, dangerous in Faith. The 4. fals. The 5. fals &amp; prejudicial to the authority of Councils. The 6. scandalous, &amp; blasphemous. The 7. contrary to common right, temerarious, &amp; tending to the destruction of the Church. What bitternes against the Pope? what at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt against the Spiritual Monarchy of the Church? Mean while the learned defender of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172251:28"/>Monsieur Vernant, opposes against thes cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, in his Book <hi>of the ancient doctrine of the Divines of Paris,</hi> the true doctrine &amp; formal words of the Gen. Councils, of Nice 1. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, Calcedon, Nice 2. Constantinople 4. Florentin &amp; others. He opposes the practise of the first ages, &amp; the testimonies of the Holy Fathers, Ireneus &amp; Cyprian Bishops &amp; Martyrs, Cyrill Patriark of Alexandria, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius, Austin, Optatus, Tertullian and many others. He opposes the Constitutions of Popes, that governed the Church in the first ages. He opposes the clear &amp; vnquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable judgment of S. Thomas and S. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, of Cardinal Turrecremata &amp; others, of Peter d'Alliac great Master of Navar, &amp; afterwards Bishop of Cambray, of Monsieur Raconis Bishop of Vaure, Henry of Gand, Monsieur Bail yet living, du Val, Almain, Isambert, Gamache, &amp; infinite other ancient devines, all Doctors of Sorbon, whos Books were approved by divers of the same Faculty, who have not published their works. He quotes, &amp; faithfully translates their Texts, he clearly expounds their reasons, &amp; lastly adds all the decrees and censures of that Academy against the Heresies contrary to the Catholike doctrine, of the Popes spiritual authority, which he teaches with Monsieur de Vernant.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172251:29"/>So that I cannot see, how the Sorbonists can answear him, vnles they have the secret, to prove that truth is falshood, &amp; faith heresy, &amp; that falshood is truth and heresy Orthodox Faith.</p>
                  <p>In the Collection of divers peeces printed at Munster 1666. of which I have already spoken, they are strangely transported against Alexander VII. &amp; his Bull, in which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned their Censures against Monsieur Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, &amp; Amideus Guimenius, <hi>I say they are strangely transported,</hi> for they acknowlege, &amp; evidently attest themselves to be Authors of thos writings, by thes words <hi>VVe,</hi> which they repeat 21. times. <hi>pag.</hi> 126. 127. 138. 142. 143. 144. 150. 151. and <hi>Our Censures,</hi> which they vse 8. several times <hi>pag.</hi> 126. 129. 138. 142. 144. 145. 146. 147. Besides their not disow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that furious Libell, by an authentical Censure, puts it out of question, that they approve it as their own work. I have a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to transcribe their injuries against A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander VII <hi>pag.</hi> 97. They call his Bull the greatest monster that was ever seen in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church. They cal it &amp; strive to prove it <hi>temerarious, pag.</hi> 100. 101. <hi>presumptuous, pag.</hi> 101. <hi>scandalous, pag.</hi> 102. 103. <hi>vnjust &amp; full of nullities, pag.</hi> 123. <hi>grounded vpon principles that are manifestly heretical, pag.</hi> 101. <hi>authorizing clear
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172251:29"/>heresies, pag.</hi> 123. <hi>That ther is just reason, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse &amp; condemn it for heretical, pag.</hi> 104. <hi>That it agmes to destroy the Church, pag.</hi> 113. <hi>That we cannot receave it, without turning the Church topsy turvy &amp; without an entier abjuration of all the Chief maximes of the Ghospel, pag.</hi> 124. <hi>That Alexander VII. rashly depends vpon divine inspiration, pag.</hi> 100. <hi>That he fals into new errours as he had done into old ones, pag.</hi> 107. <hi>That he has made a fals supposition, injurious to the Faculty, pag.</hi> 138. <hi>That he made his Bull without discussing, without examining, &amp; without so much as seing the Facultys Censure, pag.</hi> 130. Though the Pope declare the contrary in his Bull, <hi>habitis,</hi> says he <hi>prius doctissimorum &amp;c. consultationibus. That his infallibility is a mere chimera &amp; a mere politick &amp; cabinet device, to deceave ignorant &amp; weake spirits, &amp; to vsurp an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just authority over the people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 131. 108. 151. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lastly they accuse Pope Honorius, John XXII. &amp;c. <hi>of errours &amp; heresies.</hi> pag. 140. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They repeat the same accusations, in the Apology for their Censures, approved by 7. Doctors of the Faculty, &amp; that which is very strange, they took them out of the Books of the Lutherans, Protestants, &amp; Calvinists, for all the solid answears of Cardinal Perron, &amp; Father Coeffeteau, have invincible proved them fals. After which, it cannot be denied, but the Sorbonists surpasse their Masters, in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:172251:30"/>this hatred: for the Jansenists dealt more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately with Innocent X. &amp; Alexander VII. &amp; their Constitutions, by which their Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies were condemned. Du Moulin himself, Son to the famous Minister of that name, &amp; Prebend of Canturbury, is more reserved in his <hi>Discours of a Burgher of Paris,</hi> vpon the Legation of Cardinal Ghisi, printed at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don 1665. Ther is not a sincere Catholike, who is not easily persuaded by so strong and convincing Proofs, that the Sorbonists being, as they are, the Popes professed enemies, are direct Jansenists.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proof">
                  <head>The sixt Proof.</head>
                  <p>Their hatred to Religious persons, is a 6. Proof. The Jansenists conspired against Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, as I obserued in their Policy, from the beginning of their Cabal; foreseing wel, that they would put obstacles to the establishment of their Heresies. And they have often ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually felt, the force of so great a body. All the world knows, that the heresies of Monsieur Arnaud, were censured in the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, because as Montalte writes, in his 1. <hi>Letter</hi> Colen Edit. <hi>pag.</hi> 23. <hi>Ther stood for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> 24. <hi>secular Doctors &amp; about</hi> 40. <hi>Mendicant Monks who condemned his Proposition.</hi> Which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:172251:30"/>deadly blow gave them such a deep wound, that since that time, they have openly profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by a thousand vnjust proceedings, the inveterate hatred to Religious. The Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists exactly follow their steps. They have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by their censure; all the Propositions which Monsieur Vernant advanced in favour of the Regulars Privileges, though he brought nothing but the express doctrine, &amp; formal words of Gen. Councils, Popes Bulls, Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, ancient Doctors of Sorbon, &amp; other Catholike Authors. Which the learned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender has confirmed by many irrefragable testimonies. Moreover they have quite ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them out of their Assemblies in the Sorbon, to remove by their exclusion, thos obstacles which hindered them from judging of the questions proposed, according to their passion. And truly, the number of Catholike Doctors being at present the lesser in the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, the Jansenists have the advantage, to the great dishonour of the Faculty, whos censures would never have been condemned by the Pope as they have been, if Regulars had been there, for they would have been conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Orthodox faith. In fine the Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists strive to make Regulars odious, by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Collection of divers peeces <hi>pag.</hi> 111. num. 18. <hi>That the Popes Bull, as fals it is, is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:172251:31"/>maintaind in France by twenty thousand, partly Monks, &amp; partly interressed Ecclesiasticks, &amp; that ther is nothing, that ought not to be feared from them &amp; pag.</hi> 142. <hi>That a dozen Regulars, with whom the Pope consulted, prevails against</hi> 200. <hi>Sorbon Doctors.</hi> Since Hereticks both ancient &amp; modern, have always cruelly hated Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, what must we judge of the Sorbon, and in what rank must we place them since they have the like hatred.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proof">
                  <head>The seventh Proof.</head>
                  <p>Take the last resemblance they have with the Jansenists, Ther is no dissimulation, disguise, cheat or imposture, which thes He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks do not vse, against their adversaries. Montalte is the cunningest at it in the world, in his first Letters, against the Censure of Monsieur Arnauds heresies, opposite to the Catholike doctrine, of sufficient grace, and contrary to the Dominicans &amp; other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik Doctours. And in his last, he attributes to the Jesuits at a venture, all the strangest Maxims, he could devise. Wheras thos Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in their Apologies, prove the perfect harmony, between thos slanders, and thos which du Moulin heretofore, cast vpon the Roman Church. Besides they convince the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:172251:31"/>Jansenists of 29. evident impostures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind in 8. Lettres of Montalte, viz: the 11.12. &amp;c. And in their last answears, they lay open the other calumnies of thes Hereticks, which the Sorbonists exactly imitate. And truly the defender of Monsieur Vernant, in his Book of the antient divinity of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, complains in his Preface &amp; <hi>pag.</hi> 519. that they attribute vnto Monsieur Vernant, a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, of which he makes not the least men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the 176.384.388. pages quoted by the Censurers, nor in his whol Book. He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves 495. that in the extract of censured Propositions, <hi>pag.</hi> 630. they slip over vnder thes points (.......) the reasons &amp; proofs, by which they are authorized. In the 426.427. <hi>pages</hi> he charges them with making fals suppositions, and perverting the sense of the propositions drawn out of <hi>pag.</hi> 365.366. &amp; then proves them to be Orthodox, if not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by their malicious explication. In his whol Book <hi>Of the Ancient doctrine of the devines of Paris,</hi> he clearly demonstrates, that they took no notice, of Monsieur de Vernant his proofs, drawn out of the Authors, which I cited in my 5. Proof. That they slighted his reasons, &amp; maliciously interpreted his words. And that in condemning him, they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned vnder his name, the Councils Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:172251:32"/>Popes, their own Devines, all foraign Doctors, the most eminent in dignity, the most famous for learning, &amp; zeal for the true Faith. So true is that, which Lactantius says, that they oppugn the truth, &amp; will not see it, least acknowleging their innocency, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, against their errours, they should not be able to condemn them, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest injustice. <hi>Student damnare tamquam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, quos vtique sciunt innocentes; constare de ipsa innocentia nolunt: verentur enim quod si au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dierint, damnare non possint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what shal I say, of their Censure of Amadeus Guymenius? In good earnest, I dislike, &amp; had I sufficient authority, would condemn, his manner of defending the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits, against the Dominicans. Tis true he proves wel, that the Dominicans, have taught worse opinions then the Jesuits; but to what purpose is it, to let the people see, so many odious opinions, bundled vp in a litle vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn? I wonder the Jesuits, had so litle Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, as not to hinder, if they could, the printing of that Book, especially at a time, when they had so many professed enemies. Yet because I only vndertake, to prove the Sorbonists falsifying, &amp; impostures without meddling with their doctrine, I will set down the foul calumnies, which they cast vpon
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:172251:32"/>Guimenius; not all: it were too trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, but some of the most conspicuous.</p>
                  <p>In the Propositions, which they censured, viz the 4. they have cut off Guimenius his words, &amp; so alterd his sense. <hi>pag.</hi> 86. <hi>n.</hi> 2.3. In the 7. they suppress the good sense of Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius his words <hi>pag.</hi> 87. <hi>n.</hi> 3. In the 9. they dissemble, that Guimenius answears Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; that the Jesuits are of a contrary opinion, <hi>pag.</hi> 94. <hi>n.</hi> 1. In the 15. they impose vpon Guimenius, by cutting of the last words of the Proposition. <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <hi>num.</hi> 3. In the 25. they make Guimenius approve an opinion, which he says, is not to be maintained <hi>pag.</hi> 127. In the 27. They take no notice, that Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius holds the contrary, rejecting <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ajetan &amp; Sylvester, both Dominicans, <hi>pag.</hi> 237. In the 33. Guimenius rejects it, <hi>pag.</hi> 114. <hi>n.</hi> 5. In the 37. all the Jesuits deny it, &amp; reject it with S. Antonin, <hi>pag.</hi> 158 <hi>n.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the 47. They are the very tearmes, &amp; proper doctrine of S. Thomas, whos words they mangled, to corrupt the sense, that they might condemn it. <hi>pag.</hi> 109. <hi>n.</hi> 3. In the 54. They are Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus his words, who lays a horrible calumny vpon Sanchez, whos words &amp; sense are quite contrary, <hi>pag.</hi> 34. <hi>n.</hi> 2. How then came the Sorbonists to approve him? In the 59. they suppress the name of Sotus, and Guimenius
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:172251:33"/>his words, to make their Censure, fall vpon the Jesuits, <hi>pag.</hi> 142. In the 61. they omitt Guimenius his words, who says that Claudius Aquaviva, General of the Jesuits, forbad them to teach publickly, or privatly, or to practise such kind of opinions, <hi>pag.</hi> 210. In the 69. they are the words of the Roman Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal, quoted by S. Antonin and yet they condemn them. <hi>pag.</hi> 221. <hi>n.</hi> 1! In the 70 Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius rejects it, as contrary to the Council of Trent. <hi>pag.</hi> 233. <hi>n.</hi> 5. He does the same in the 72. <hi>pag.</hi> 277. <hi>num.</hi> 18. In the 75. they have not drawn it out faithfully, and besides it is the opinion of Sylvester. <hi>pag.</hi> 177. <hi>n.</hi> 4. In the 77. It is Anonymus his doctrine, which Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius rejects with horrour. <hi>pag.</hi> 285. propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition 5. <hi>num</hi> 2. In the 79. they cut off, by a strange infidelity, Guimenius his words, which justify him. <hi>pag.</hi> 284. <hi>n.</hi> 3. In the 80. they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciously leave out Guimenius his answear, who confutes his accuser. <hi>pag.</hi> 244. Prop. 2. In the 81. they confirme the horrible Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of Anonymus against Vasquez, who has not a word of the proposition censured <hi>pag.</hi> 25. Proposit. 12 In the 15. Propositions, which they cite only by their first words, it is only Anonymus, that advanced them, Guimenius maintains, that the Jesuits detest them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the censured Propositions ther are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:172251:33"/>28. of Anonymus &amp; 44. of other Authors, no Jesuits, &amp; yet the Sorbonists, attribute them all to Guimenius, that they might have occasion to censure them, &amp; the Jesuits in his person, because he relates the calumnies, with which he defiles their doctrine and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
                  <p>From thes Proofs, which are all in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Fact,</hi> it is easy to conclude, that the Sorbonists, exactly follow, the false dealing, &amp; cheating way of the Jansenists. Had they proceeded, as Catholike Doctors ought to do, according to rules of conscience, and Christian sincerity, they would have censured the Propositions, vnder the names of their Authors, whom they should have named, &amp; not have taxed the Jesuits, to satisfy the hatred they bear them. Who in the mean time, have this advantage against the Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, that Heresy cannot be justly layd in their dish.</p>
                  <p>Behould Sir, the deplorable state of our Faculty, which you will not question, if you take but the pains, to consider with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, the Proofs which I have set down. And how should they not be infected, with the Jansenists heresies, since they drew them from the beginning, out of the writings, &amp; publick lessons of Saint Beuve, who chose
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:172251:34"/>rather, to renounce his degree &amp; chayre of Doctour, then Jansenisme? Since they obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately defend their errours? Since they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove &amp; cry vp their Books &amp; Translations in which they deliver their errours? Since they do not censure, &amp; condemn thos that renew them? Since they Censure the Books of Catholicks their enemies? Since they have a mortal hatred for the Pope, as all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks have? Since they bear the same hatred to Religious, because they destroy heresy &amp; defend the Catholike Faith? Since they vse the same tricks, &amp; the same calumnies, to censure them, &amp; to tarnish the lustre of their reputation, which thes Novellists em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, against Orthodox Doctors? All thes Caracters, being equally common to them, force vs to confess, that they have the same opinions, the same design, and the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests with the Jansenists.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
                  <p>I draw 2. necessary Conclusions, out of the whol discours. The first. That Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der VII. has with a great deal of justice, in his Bull of Jun. 1665. condemned, the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon Censures, of Monsieur de Vernant, &amp;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:172251:34"/>Guimenius, as <hi>Presumptuous, Temerarious, Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous,</hi> &amp; forbidden them, vnder pain of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, reserving the Absolution vnto himself.</p>
                  <p>The second. That the Decrees of thes Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, their Decisions, and their Censures ought hereafter to be suspected by Catholiks: That one ought not easily to believe, that the Books they approve, are free from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy: Finally that one ought not to adhere to their opinions, vntill they have renounced Jansenisme, as Monsieur R. cald Montalte, Author of the Provincial Letters, did before his death, with such signs of a true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that it is to be hoped that God let him feel the effects of his mercy.</p>
                  <p>For my part, I am fane to lye concealed, &amp; keep close vpon my gard, to avoid the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of my fellow Doctors, who would furiously handle me, did they know, that I am the man, that have so sincerely set down thes things, which I send you for great truths. Yet they shal not hinder me, from giving immortal thanks, vnto the Father of all grace, who by his amiable goodnes, has drawn we out of errour and precipice. Give you also thanks, Sir, I beseech you, &amp; beleeve if you please, that I am entierly yours in CHRIST JESVS. <hi>This</hi> 21. <hi>May.</hi> 1667.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:172251:35"/>
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Iansenian Propositions condemned for Heretical by the sea Apostolick.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The first.</hi> Some of Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are impossible to just men, though they desire &amp; endeavour to keep them according to their present forces: grace is also wanting in them to make them possible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The second.</hi> In the state of corrupt nature interiour grace is never resisted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third.</hi> To merit &amp; demerit in the state of corrupt nature a mans li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from necessity is not required, but liberty from coaction is sufficient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth.</hi> The Semipelagians ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the necessity of interiour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting grace, to all acts, even to the beginning of Faith, &amp; in this were Hereticks, that they would have this grace to be such that a mans will might resist it or obey it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fift.</hi> It is Semipelagianisme to say, that Christ died, or shed his blood generally for all men.</p>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:172251:35"/>
                  <head>The Censure of the sayd Propositions.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Extracted out of the Constitution of his Holines</hi> Pope Innocent X.</head>
                  <p>Primam. <hi>Aliqua Dei praecepta homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus justis volentibus &amp; conantibus secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum praesentes quas habent vires sunt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilia: deest quoque illis gratia qua pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilia fiant:</hi> Temerariam, impiam, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemam, anathemate damnatam, &amp; haereticam declaramus, &amp; vti talem damnamus.</p>
                  <p>Secundam. <hi>Interiori gratiae in statu naturae lapsae nunquam restititur:</hi> haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam declaramus &amp; vti talem damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</p>
                  <p>Tertiam. <hi>Ad merendum &amp; demeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in statu naturae lapsae non requiritur in homine libertas à necessitate, sed suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit libertas à coactione.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quartam. <hi>Semipelagiani admittebant praevenientis gratiae interioris necessitatem ad singulos actus etiam ad initium fidei: &amp; in hoc erant haeretici quod vellent eam gratiam talem esse cui potest humana volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:172251:36"/>resistere vel obtemperare:</hi> falsam &amp; haereticam declaramus &amp; vti talem dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus.</p>
                  <p>Quintam. <hi>Semipelagianum est dicere Christum pro omnibus omnino hominibus mortuum esse aut sanguinem fudisse:</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam, temerariam scandalosam, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectam eo sensu <hi>vt Christus pro salute duntaxat Praedestinatorum mortuus sit,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam blasphemam contumeliosam, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae pietati derogantem &amp; haereticam declaramus &amp; vti talem damnamus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Another Extract out of the Constitution of his Holines</hi> Pope Alexander VII.</head>
                  <p>In which having recited his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours Constitution he does not only confirme his Censures but further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the 5. Propositions to be taken out of Iansenius &amp; to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the sense intended by the sayd Iansenius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Cùm autem, sicut acccpimus, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli iniquitatis filii praedict as quinque Propositiones, vel in libro praedicto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusdem
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:172251:36"/>Cornelii Jansenii non reperiri, sed fictè &amp; pro arbitrio compositas esse, vel non in sensu ab eodem intento damnatas fuisse, asserere, magno cum Christi fidelium scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalo, non reformident, Nos qui omnia, quae hac in re gesta sunt sufficienter &amp; attentè per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speximus, vtpote qui ejusdem Innocentii Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessoris jussu, dum adhuc in minoribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituti Cardinalatus munere fungeremur, omnibus congressibus interfuimus, in quibus Apostolicâ authoritate eadem caussa discussa est eâ profectò diligentia, qua major deside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari non posset, quamcumque dubitationem super praemissis in posterum auferre volentes, vt omnes Christi fideles in ejusdem fidei vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate sese contineant: ex debito nostri Pastora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis officii, ac matura deliberatione praeinsertam Innocentii Praedecessoris nostri Constitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, declarationem &amp; definitionem, harum serie confirmamus, approbamus, &amp; innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; quinque illas Propositiones, ex libro praememorati Cornelii Jansenii Iprensis, cui titulus est, <hi>Augustinus,</hi> excerptas, ac in sensu ab eodem Cornelio intento damnatas fuisse declaramus, &amp; definimus; &amp; vti tales, inusta scilicet eadem singulis nota, quae in praedicta declaratione, &amp; definitione, vnicuique illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum sigillatim inuritur, iterum damnamus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:172251:37"/>
                  <head>THE FORMVLA <hi>To be subscribed by all Ecclesiasticks in France in submission to ALEXANDER the VII. his Bull which condemns Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senius his errours: prescribed by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assembly of the Clergy &amp; sent to the other Prelats of the Kingdome the</hi> 17. <hi>of March,</hi> 1657.</head>
                  <p>I Sincerely submit my self to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of Pope Innocent X. of the 31. of May 1653. according to the true sense therof which was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Constitution of our Holy Father Pope ALEXANDER VII. on the 16 Octob. 1656. I acknowlege that I am obliged in conscience to obey thes Constitutions, &amp; I condemne in hart &amp; in word the doctrine of the 5. Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of Cornelius Iansenius, containd in his Book cald <hi>Augustinus,</hi> which thes two Popes and the Bishops have condemned: which doctrine is not S. Austins, whom Iansenius has inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted against the true sense of the Holy Doctour.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:172251:37"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>